<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ROOT xmlns="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.weareavp.com/nunncenter/ohms/ohms.xsd">
  <record id="1" dt="2022-09-01">
    <version>5.4</version>
    <date value="2021-08-03" format="yyyy-mm-dd"/>
    <date_nonpreferred_format>21-08-2020</date_nonpreferred_format>
    <cms_record_id>CMSRecordID</cms_record_id>
    <title>Test</title>
    <accession>test-0001</accession>
    <duration>00:30:00</duration>
    <collection_id>Q3sWOVJfNwQCollectionID</collection_id>
    <collection_name>CollectionName</collection_name>
    <series_id>SeriesID</series_id>
    <series_name>SeriesName</series_name>
    <repository>Public</repository>
    <funding>Acknowledgment</funding>
    <repository_url>public</repository_url>
    <subject>Subjects 1</subject>
    <subject>Subjects 2</subject>
    <keyword>Interview 1</keyword>
    <keyword>Interview 2</keyword>
    <interviewee>Raza</interviewee>
    <interviewee>Saleem</interviewee>
    <interviewer>Nouman</interviewer>
    <interviewer>Tayyab</interviewer>
    <format>Mp4</format>
    <format>Avi</format>
    <file_name>test-0001</file_name>
    <sync>ranscript Sync Data</sync>
    <sync_alt>anscript Sync Data Translation</sync_alt>
    <transcript_alt_lang>Nepali</transcript_alt_lang>
    <translate>1</translate>
    <media_id/>
    <media_url>https://evolvr.aviaryplatform.com/embed/media/51123</media_url>
    <mediafile>
      <host>Aviary</host>
      <avalon_target_domain>www.youtube.com</avalon_target_domain>
      <host_account_id>Q3sWOVJfNwQHostAccount</host_account_id>
      <host_player_id>Q3sWOVJfNwQHostPlayer</host_player_id>
      <host_clip_id>Q3sWOVJfNwQHostItem</host_clip_id>
      <clip_format>video</clip_format>
    </mediafile>
    <kembed>&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Q3sWOVJfNwQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</kembed>
    <language>English</language>
    <user_notes>User Notes</user_notes>
    <index>
      <point>
        <time>5</time>
        <title>ok 2</title>
        <title_alt>ok2 alt</title_alt>
        <partial_transcript/>
        <partial_transcript_alt/>
        <synopsis/>
        <synopsis_alt/>
        <keywords/>
        <keywords_alt/>
        <subjects/>
        <subjects_alt/>
        <gpspoints>
          <gps/>
          <gps_zoom>0</gps_zoom>
          <gps_text/>
          <gps_text_alt/>
        </gpspoints>
        <hyperlinks>
          <hyperlink/>
          <hyperlink_text/>
          <hyperlink_text_alt/>
        </hyperlinks>
      </point>
      <point>
        <time>26</time>
        <title>test eerrrr</title>
        <title_alt>test eerrrr aslt</title_alt>
        <partial_transcript/>
        <partial_transcript_alt/>
        <synopsis/>
        <synopsis_alt/>
        <keywords/>
        <keywords_alt/>
        <subjects/>
        <subjects_alt/>
        <gpspoints>
          <gps/>
          <gps_zoom>0</gps_zoom>
          <gps_text/>
          <gps_text_alt/>
        </gpspoints>
        <hyperlinks>
          <hyperlink/>
          <hyperlink_text/>
          <hyperlink_text_alt/>
        </hyperlinks>
      </point>
    </index>
    <type>video</type>
    <description>Summary</description>
    <rel/>
    <transcript>﻿STILL:  Okay, so, so my name is Valerie Still[[footnote]]1[[/footnote]], I'm conducting an interview with Lillian Nareen White-Washington on February 4th, 2021 for the U.K. Women's Basketball Oral History Project for the Louie B. Nunn Center for Oral History at the University of Kentucky. Wow. First um, Lillian, let me say it's quite an honor and a pleasure to have you as my second interviewee of the U.K. Women's Basketball Oral History Project, the mother of UK women's basketball, who you know as your head coach Sue Feamster--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --right--

STILL:  --was my first interviewee. And as I was researching Sue, I came across the official team photo for the 1975, ‘76 team and my mouth dropped as I noticed a young black, uh person of color--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --mhmm--

STILL:  --sitting cross-legged on the floor. When I when I had arrived that UK in1979, my roommate was Deborah Oden--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --okay--

STILL:  --a senior who I believed for all these years to have been the first African-American female basketball player in UK[[footnote]]2[[/footnote]]. Instead, I couldn't   figure out who that young girl was--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(laughs)--

STILL:  --sitting right underneath Sue Feamster. So the next day I get uh an email from Ruth Bryan, who's been helping me. She's with the UK Special Collections, and she told me that Renetta Jones [Reinette Jones], one of the librarians there who works with the special collection--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --okay--

STILL:  --who founded and maintains the No, um, Notable Kentucky and African-American--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --mhmm--

STILL:  --database, thought I should interview the first African-American female player at UK, Lillian Nareen White. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --mhmm--

STILL:  --what a coincidence. So I contacted, of course, Renetta [Reinette] right away, and she connected me with you. It's incredible. You were not only the first African-American female basketball player at UK, but you were also one of the first female players to receive a basketball scholarship at UK, a five-four forward--take this forward guard from Georgetown, Kentucky. Number forty one. Now, we'll talk about that a little later-- 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --okay--

STILL:  --because I- there was another player that looked like they had forty one, but we'll talk about that as well. But this is just extra special for me,   especially when you consider what's going on in our country right now with women of color, from the brave young congresswomen of color that are standing up and making their voice heard for justice. To Stacey Abrams in Georgia, who was the deciding factor in our two, 2020 presidential and 2021 Senate elections to that incredible young, beautiful poet, Amanda Gordon, who shared her poetry at um, the inauguration of 2021 to the courage, courageous women, brave women of the WNBA who have not only decided to have a voice in our society in terms of social justice, but to make that voice loud and clear, not just taking a knee like the, the guys have been doing for social justice. But I don't know if you saw this, --(sniffs)-- during their season this summer, in the bubble down in Florida, during a pandemic, they walked out of the playing of the national anthem and then them being a major factor for Georgia electing its first African-American and Jewish senators to--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --right--

STILL:  --of course, as we all know, the election of our first   female Vice President and a woman of color, Kamala Harris. Wow.--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --mhmm, right--

STILL:  --so finding you and being able to have you talk to tell your story, your history, your legacy in this new UK women's oral history project, it's just quite the honor for me. You, I cannot tell you enough. I know when you were at UK, you were known as Nareen--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --right--

STILL:  --but for family, you told me it's Lillian and I should call you Lillian. So now I’m going to call--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --no, call me Nareen--

STILL:  -- you Lillian. No, Nareen?--

WHITE-WASHINGTON: --Nareen, yes--

STILL:  --Okay, okay, so it's Nareen is the opposite, there there’s my-

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --[right]--

STILL: --but I'm going to--I just, thank you, my lady cat sister. And for the record, can you just please give us your official name and your affiliation with UK, and then the years that you were at UK, and then we'll get started from there. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  [Okay]. My official name is Lillian Nareen White-Washington. And my name, Lillian[[footnote]]3[[/footnote]], it started   being Lillian when I got into the sector of jobs here in Georgetown, because that's what they call you, your first name, Lillian. And I never really corrected them, I didn't say, well I want to be called Nareen, so it's Nareen.

STILL:  Oh, so it is Nareen. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Mhmm.

STILL:  So that's when I when I told--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --and, and I (??) with Lillian--

STILL:  --(laughs) what I--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --nobody knows me as Lillian, really. 

STILL:  --(laughs) (??)--

WHITE WASHINGTON:  --[they say who is Lillian?] So--

STILL:  --(laughs)--exactly, exactly. So where did you get that name? Tell us a little bit about you. Your childhood, where you come from, a little bit about your family, parents, siblings. Just give us a little background on your childhood history. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Well, I was named after my father's mother, which her name is Narsis. Instead of them calling me Narsis, my mom said, no, we going to put the ‘reen’ on it, so it's Nareen. And then my step grandmother, her name was Lillian, so she wanted me to be named after her, too. So what they did, they decided to say,   Lillian, which is my uh, step grandmother, and Nareen, which is my father's mother. Our (??) had been called Narsis since the ‘reen’ is just everybody ignoring that ‘reen’ part, so I would rather had been called Narsis, last name White, which of course comes from my, my mom and my dad. Um, I was born the third child of six kids, which I'm the middle one. And it was three, it was four girls and two boys. So um, I had always been a very athletic person. And I was always really, even though I was older than my brother, I was under my brother and I didn't think that was fair because anything that we did, I always won. We played basketball, I won, anything that we did, running. We used to have to run against each other, I would win. So, you know, comp, uh competing and uh,   striving to be the best. I was born into that. 

STILL:  And during, tell us a little bit about you're from Georgetown--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --right--

STILL:  --that's, what, about ten, twenty miles from uh Lexington?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??)--

STILL:  Tell us a little bit about your--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --Oh it’s, you could really walk there, it’s really that it's not even that far from George, from Lexington--

STILL:  --Okay, okay--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --Lexington, Georgetown, it’s very close.--

STILL:   --So tell us a little bit about--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --[maybe about]--

STILL:  --your community, your neighborhood. What was that like growing up? You were born in the ‘50s, I want to say--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --I was born in the ‘50s. 

STILL:  Okay, so what was that like, um, your town? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  You know what, it was a very loving town. You know, we, we were raised, and not to see color, but we always had to um, it was like we were shielded, we were protected. So we didn't really see color. Everything was had what you did and how you did it. 

STILL:  Did you grow up, was it a predominantly uh, black neighborhood or was it uh--  

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --our neighborhood was known as called Boston. 

STILL:  Mhmm. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  And um, it was a black neighborhood. We had very few whites in the neighborhood, but we had whites in the neighborhood, Caucasian people. But it was predominantly black and it was a really, really, it wasn’t really a neighborhood. I mean, you didn't have to lock your doors. Everybody knew one another. You know, if you did something wrong, you got in trouble with your neighbors. Our parents didn't have to worry about getting babysitters because your next door neighbor would babysit with your, without your mom even asking, can you babysit my kids? So you know, our, my mom would go to work and come back because my mom and, and dad divorced at a young age when I was younger. And so I would go back and forth from um Georgetown to Columbus, Ohio, where my dad lived--

STILL:  --Oh, wow--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --which is with his grandmother and his mother, which is my grandmother, Narsis. So we lived in a beaut--I mean, everything was so close.   We were close knit and we had that’s all we did was run and play ball all day long. Marbles--

STILL:  --(laughs)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --and uh, basket, box hockey at the park, softball, basketball, and I loved football. 

STILL:  Now, none of that was organized, was it because in the 1950s, for girls, what opportunities did you have as a young, you know, girl of color as well? Uh, what were the opportunities, sports-wise?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  To be honest, we had none. Everything I did, I did with the boys. So and, you know, I always had to out-do someone. I always had to be the best. So, you know, with I played basketball, I had to win. If I played football, I had to win. If I ran, I just had to win. So everything was comp, was competitive with me. I was I think I was born into competition. I was competitive, always--

STILL:  --Wow so that’s in your nature--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??) even, even with my siblings. Nobody could pick on them.   Nobody could say anything to them because I always wanted to always step up and say, you don't talk to my brother or sister like that. You know, I've always been, I felt, the protector of, of, of my siblings. 

STILL:  Now, when did you start playing, uh I'm going to say organized sport as far as in high school, middle school? When did you start playing on team sports? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Track, which will be the first (??) that I played--

STILL: --okay, was that like in middle school, or did you start at a younger age? Or did it start in high school? In middle school?

WHITE-WASHINGTON: -- (??)That, that would’ve been in middle school, but our middle school was our high school because we only graduated with in between thirty kids at thirty, thirty (??)--

STILL:  --wow. What high school was that?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  That was Georgetown High School. We had two high schools, Georgetown High School and Scott County and Georgetown never had a middle school. You come right out of the sixth grade into the seventh grade, which we were considered high school because we all went to school together from seventh to the twelfth. 

STILL:  And you said that was a fairly   small um, school. Was that an integrated school or was it segregated or was?--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --It was integrated, it was integrated.

STILL:  Wow, but it was small. You said seven, how many students did you say? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  We had, if we had twenty if we had thirty kids to graduate, we had to have right about maybe, mmm, I'll say a good four or five hundred, maybe less than that-- 

STILL:  --wow, so--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --because we (??)--

STILL:  --and that was high school, that’s high school was like that as well. So who were you competing against? Were you competing when you when you were playing organized sport or track and field? Uh, you all were playing um schools across the state of Kentucky then?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Uh, at the time, yes we were. We were, we were, track was the first sport. And we, we competed uh with everybody. Uh we competed with our, our, our school was single-A, but we competed with single-A, triple-A.   It didn't matter until we really got into like uh, a district play or whatever you, you were uh like the CK, we were CKC, and then you had the, the, uh, county schools and everybody had they own, um, as you say, like. Everybody would, like your district. We already, you know, had your region and a district, but I don't think it was too much like that. But it, yes, at the end it was, because we would always win our district. But it was just hard when we got into the region because you, you had um girls that, or boys, that were bigger. And as it moved on, you know, we were always outnumbered because it was a small school. So we was always out uh, competitively. We were always out--

STILL:  --okay--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --um, strengthened. We was always the weakest to a po--certain degree.   Because we didn't have a lot of students or we didn't have a lot of kids that were really active, like track. We didn't have a lot of girls that really could run. 

STILL:  Mhmm. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  You know, uh, they would come out for the team and it would be it, but with myself, I made it a everyday thing. You know, to me, it was it was it was everything that I wanted to be. I would always watched um track and field on TV. And I always kept up with the Tennessee Tiger Bales. 

STILL:  Oh, yeah. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  And Temple. I always kept up with them. Even when I was young--

STILL:  --mhmm--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --I always kept up with them. 

STILL:  --(coughs)--Nareen. I can just hear I think there might be, uh is there a TV on? Or, I just want to make sure. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Just a second. 

STILL:  --(laughs)--  

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I had to turn the TV off and (??)--

STILL:  --I just, for some, but hey, the beauty of, you know, oral history during a pandemic virtually so uh it’s that's much better. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(laughs)--

STILL:  And we want to get your stories important. So I, I've read that from seventh grade until, this can't be right. You were undefeated from seventh grade to twelfth grade? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON: Yes, I was. I was undefeated. That, it was, you know, running track to me, it got to be an art. 

STILL:  Wow. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  And I, I really started studying it, and my whole thing about running was then I started playing with it, I   start to um, you know, what could I do different today to make this race interesting? And I always liked running from the back. 

STILL:  --which--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I always let everyone pass me. 

STILL:  Which events were you running and um, participating in? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I-I ran the eight, eight-eighty. 

STILL:  Wow.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  That was always the last race of the day. 

STILL:  Uh-huh.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  But between that, I would always, sometimes I would run the four hundred meters. But my specialty was relays, I, I ran the eight-eighty medley relay, which at the end I ran, I anchored it. So I had to run for four-forty with a two-twenty, uh another two-twenty, a one-ten, and then a four-forty. 

STILL:  Wow.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  But we, no, I take that back. We had a two hundred, which was the two-twenty, we had one-ten, a one-ten, and then I anchored it with the uh, with the four, four hundred. So I always ran from the back. 

STILL:  Wow, all that um track and field made   you a great athlete, but to play basketball, how did that come about? You have to have certain skills for basketball. Who got you interested in basketball and how and why? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Well, you know, everybody uh in the neighborhood uh didn't run. So I thought I'd have to play basketball with the guys, which I did. And it got to be to the point where I didn't want to, want to lose. So I played with a lot of the guys that were very good, so I had to think of ways to outplay them if, if they were six foot something, I had to figure out a way to be able to beat them. So I was quicker so I could go to the rim, uh get to the rim quicker. Uh I think I was even boxing out before they even thought about boxing out, because if I could keep them off the rim, then I could get the rebound, put it back up. And then they started saying, ah you got to take it back, you got to take it back. So I don't know if this   was invented by us or not --(both laugh)-- You always had to take the ball back, give them a chance to set up. So um, that's really how I started playing basketball. And then we start going and playing on teams. And I was, they didn't pick me at first until they realized, well she can really play. And then that really made me play even harder. It even made me realize what I really had to do to be a good player, to out-play someone else, to position myself. And those are the things that you learn-- 

STILL:  --’cause five-four--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??)--

STILL:  --it, it were you stretching it, saying you were listed at five-four, are you a true five-four? Um, five-foot-four. 

WHITE-WASHINGTONI:  (??) did I? Did I list myself as five-five? That was that it was as high as I could go --(both laugh)-- and being five-three five-four-- 

STILL:  --(??) look because on the roster says five-four. And when I saw five four playing forward, you know that kind of, for me, says that uh you were playing outdoors and   just what you said now and you had to compete against guys that are much bigger, so it didn't matter your size. Um that's where your competitive nature probably came, was honed in.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  And, and I think, you know, um air, when I say air, that means that I had to learn how to stay up in the air when I would play with them. Because if I could stay up in the air and so that taught me had a long jump because in long jump, when you leap into the air, then you have to really, uh make your body move to a certain a certain way that you can reach a longer destination of whoever you jump before you. So when you, you're running in the air trying to get leverage and get your, get your speed and trying to get leverage to trying to get height and leverage, so you have to be able to move everything in a different motion to get to that point. So I learned how to do that in basketball. When   I would go up for a shot and a big guy was with me, I had to learn how to kind of stay up there for just a little bit longer and be able to put it to where he could not knock it fifty feet away from the basket and make me embarrassed, so, you know, I have to think of ways, it’s just like, to, it's like an art. 

STILL:  Who were some of the players? Because this is pre-Title IX. It's always, and it’s also a time when there weren't as many opportunities for women, you know, once you get out of high school to play--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --right--

STILL:  --sports, who were some of your favorite players or some coaches or people mentors that you wanted to emulate or that encouraged you um during that time period? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  My favorite player was Otto Petty and Lewis Alcindor, which was, um, the Lakers, what’s (??) Kareem Abdul, I never liked his name, Kareem   Abdul, I always called him Lewis Alcindor--

STILL:  --uh huh--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --little coming up, you know, and I would try to master the uh, the skyhook, you know, and it's just different things that, you know, you kind of assimilate your game from, your, your, uh, defense, your offense. But I wasn't really into basketball as I, as I was into track. I wasn't really into basketball. I love playing basketball, but I really like track-- 

STILL:  --there was there was a little school, you know, a blue, blue and white school up the street that played a little basketball that has a tradition of basketball. You all weren't familiar with the, the UK Wildcats? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Nah--

STILL:  --(laughs)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --we wasn’t--

STILL:  --No way--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --I was not. I really was not. I was, it was Georgetown College--

STILL:  --uh huh--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --at the time. And that's, you know, we would always want to go over there and watch them play. And at the time, um, we weren't allowed over there. 

STILL:  At where UK? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Georgetown College

STILL:  --Georgetown,   wow. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  We um, we had to run, uh on our own, we didn't have a track, um we didn't have a track field when I was coming up, we just had to run outside behind the school and Georgetown College is just right over there. And, I will never forget this, it was an older man. Now I don’t know if I should say his name, I’m going to say his name. His name was [Ray] Jones. And he was an, a track official, which they would start the guns and they, the officials of track and field. And he was at one of the state track meets. And me being from Georgetown, when he saw that little girl take off and run, a little bitty ol’ thing, I was. And when he saw that little girl take off and run, and I always ran from the back, and I would always kick at three-thirty and then two-twenty, I would like, put it on fire. And then as I would go by, I will say, I would sometimes, I would tease, I taunt, and time and I didn't realize   I did that. And to make, to later on, when people said you was, I was very um, you know, I, I would tease people, I was arrogant, that's the word. I was very arrogant. And I wasn't. I didn't feel like I was arrogant, I just felt like that I just wanted to amuse myself, or just be amused. So I would uh do that kick and people would tell me, what, I would come just to watch you do that kick. 

STILL:  Wow. So were you--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??)--

STILL:  --on the radar by, by ‘72, Title IX passes and so women are actually starting to get athletic scholarships, but at places like Tennessee State and historically black colleges and university, track and field was already major, pre-Title IX--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --right--

STILL:  --but were you on the radar then? Were you getting some interest from colleges? Um, you're saying people were watching the way, you know, your style, your technique, were you getting interest from track and field coaches? Colleges? And basketball as well? Have that, had that, how did that   come about? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  You know, I'm going to be honest with that, I never, I, I didn't have my sights on going to college really. I, only thing that I really had my sights on at the time, was going to the Olympics. I just really wanted to run. But I knew that I had to go to college in order to run. And I know, and I knew that I, if wanted to really uh get the attention of Ed Temple, I had to be a fabulous runner because he only went with so many girls and that was my dream. That was my dream until I pulled the hamstring and I had to rethink what I wanted to do then, after I, because it was a really bad hamstring pull, a really bad hamstring pull. 

STILL:  So what were, were there other schools recruiting you before, and, and we’ll, we'll get into how Sue Feamster recruited you, but were there other schools recruiting you or, or not? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I, I can't say that, but I want to say not.

STILL:  Mhmm.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:   I've got to really   say not. Uh, and sometimes you don't understand that, but I don't and I don't really know if they were recruiting me because my coach never told me. You know, we went through so many coaches. We had so many coaches that came through, that, and so I didn't really get to uh, find out if any college wanted me or came to look at me or not. I really didn’t, would never get that opportunity to know that. 

STILL:  So, Sue Feamster.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Mhmm.

STILL:  Tell us a little bit about Sue Feamster, how you meet her. Apparently she was the one that recruited you or did you all reach out to UK? Tell us about that. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Um, I really wanted to go close, and when uh, when they came and talk to me, I think it was after a ball game, and I wanted--

STILL:  --when, when you say they, who? Who came?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  It was a young lady that I talked to, wasn’t Sue--

STILL:  --okay.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  But I did talk to someone. And I can, as remembering uh, I did talk to someone and   then I went to UK as, to a visit. And that was my first--that was my first choice, the only choice I felt, so I took that. You know, I wanted to be close to home, my mom wanted me close to home and I really wanted to be close to home. I know my family, uh, you know, everybody was really connected to Kentucky, my aunts were, she worked there. So I kind of wanted to be close, you know, to her because I didn't really know anybody anyway. So by her working there, I knew that I, if something happened, I could depend on her also. So--

STILL:  --so you make the decision, you eventually meet Sue, what was your first impression when you met Sue? Did you meet her before, or well, of course, you had to meet her before you got on campus. So what was your impression of Sue Feamster? She was uh, at that time--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??) right. She didn’t look like --

STILL:  --she was an athletic director at the school--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  -- didn’t look like no basketball coach. --(both laugh)-- But then what are basketball coaches supposed to look like?   And I'm like, you know, I'm just, you know, so not understanding. So anyway, because all my coaches were men, basketball, and then the track were men and women. And so meeting her, I'm like, oh okay. And, you know, I just felt comfortable with her. I really did, and I, make that choice, I made the choice to go to UK, because-- 

STILL:  --they, they also offered you, and these are the first scholarships that they're offering, I think Ceal Barry, who was a junior the year you came as a freshman, but I think they offered, and they were giving out partial scholarships as well. But I believe you got a scholarship or did, is that right? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Just put it like this, I didn't have to pay. --(both laugh)--I mean, I'm serious. I didn't have to pay at the time. So I went, I wasn’t going to open up my map. I just took what was given to me, you know, it’s a free education. So, you know, I just took what was given to me. 

STILL:  Wow. So you pack all your stuff right up the street, you go,   um tell me what it was like when you got to you came. What, what were you thinking UK was like? Had you been on the campus before or was this the first time?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I--

STILL:  --walk us through that whole experience--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --I went to campus. Okay, let’s see, I went on campus for that first visit and I was like, wow, this place is huge. And once I got there we were at, we checked in at the um, the hotel--

STILL:  --hotel?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --let’s see, what was the name? Yeah, we were downtown at the hotel. What was that hotel? Um, it was on my mind, but it's, it's left. It, it was the, uh--

STILL:  --see I thought there was a couple of different places. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  And um, what was it? They, it's torn down now and it's not there anymore.   And, and but it was it was on the tip of my tongue. And we stayed there until we got, until rooms opened up, so I remember that Lisa Moore was my roommate there--

STILL:  --mhmm--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --and then when, when the rooms opened up, she went somewhere and I went, I think Blazer I don't know, it was one of those halls that I went to. So I wasn't really with some of the basketball girls, some of the basketball girls had their own apartments. 

STILL:  Oh, really? So back then, the team was staying in different spots then, they weren't all on campus. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Right, right--

STILL:  --so, and you, your roommate initially was, ‘cause I don’t-- 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  It was Lisa Moore. She didn’t, Lisa Moore, she ran track. Lisa Moore ran track. 

STILL:  Okay, okay, so she wasn't a basket, I was looking on the basketball roster,

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --she wasn’t a basketball player, you know, I didn't really meet any of the basketball players until I had gotten there. And it was quite a, uh couple of days. And it really was   really I didn't really get to meet anybody until we started practicing. I didn't know anybody. 

STILL:  You didn’t know any of the players? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Debbie Mack was the only one that I knew, I knew her before uh I got to UK. I knew Debbie Mack--

STILL:  --how--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --because we uh, ran track against one another. 

STILL:  How’d that go? You and Debbie Mack running? So you guys, since what, high school, you were competing against each other, so when you got to UK, you knew her? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I knew her from running track, but I never really saw her play basketball because we were on they were,--(clears throat)-- they were, I think double-A or triple-A, we were one-A.

STILL:  Uh huh.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  And so that's how we competed. That's how you know, we knew what district, region or whatever. But we was never, we didn't start playing with the Lexington schools until after the merge. So to that, you know, I really never did get to compete with her until we got to the all-star, all-star level, which --(clears throat)-- she was, we were both, one was, we were both East and West. I think more   the Louisville girls were East and I think we were West. 

STILL:  When you arrived on campus, did you notice, you said you came from a predominantly black community, um what kind of experience it was? Was it getting on to UK in student life and campus life? And here you are surrounded? I'm pretty sure there weren't many other people of color at the University of Kentucky--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --no--

STILL:  --at that time. What was that like? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(clears throat)--It was like this. What have I gotten myself into? I, it was the most, scariest, really scariest moment of my life because everything was. But then, even knowing that you're right down the road, it's, it's not the same because you're in a foreign place. And to me, that was a foreign place because it was so big, I couldn't get over how big it was. And it was, I was already intimidated when I got there. You know, the size, and --(clears throat)-- then knowing some of the people,   which was Debbie Mack, you know, I started kind of, I don't know, I just, it wasn't a good feel. Like I say (??) feel it for the first time. It wasn't a good feel. I was. I was I felt out of place (??)--

STILL:  --But I think most, I, I remember my first experience I felt and I had been on campus a couple of times. My brother had played at UK. But I think that overwhelmingness uh most freshmens feel that when they come on uh, on a campus like UK. But um, how did you overcome that? So because initially you arrive in the fall of 1975, um the team had just been reinstated, the varsity sport, for one year, and then you come in, uh what was the orientation in that kind of thing, like classes, uh just student life? How, how did you adapt to that? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I didn't. I'm not going to lie, I did not. I did not adapt at all. Uh,   And that was my worry, and I realized that now, that was really my worry then, because it wasn't like going to um, high school and going to your math class or going to your English class. It was so different, you know, because really you are on your own. And that was something that I wasn't used to, being on my own. I was always used to my mom telling me what to do, your coach telling you what to do, your teachers telling you what to do. And I come from a family that really um, they, you were told what to do. You didn't ask questions. You just did what they told you to do. 
And then once you get on your own out there, this big world it’s like, oh, my God, I'm not prepared for this. I wasn't prepared. 

STILL:  So schedule your classes and uh freshman orientation. No one from the team, because this is the pioneer days of UK women's basketball, so they're only in varsity sport for a year.   So it's not like now when they have when those athletes come in, they're like guided through everything. Matter of fact, their classes are probably selected for them and all those kind of things. You're saying that you didn't have any one from the team that helped guide--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --mhmm--

STILL:  --wow.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Do you know what? And now that you're talking, I remember a, a, a man of color, a black man named Ed Bowers, and he was [at] Kentucky, Ed Bowers, and uh, and I think it was, it was over there in one of the buildings and I want to say more or less uh, maybe black student affairs? I don’t think that they really had at the time, the black student affairs. I, I'm not for sure, but I'm pretty sure that that's what he was in. Because of uh, I, I remember him being in that, and he stayed in that for years, you know, um and so I think it was more or less trying to recruit, you know, black people or people of color.   So that's the only thing that I'm going to say I remember. But other than me being out there by myself, I didn't have anybody to come up and say, hey, do you think you're going to need some help? Or this, we're going to take you somewhere to your classes to show you how to do this. Or if you have a lec, a lecture class, you definitely would have a lab class. I didn't know none of that. I had a lab class and didn’t even know. 

STILL:  What about your other teammates, the other freshmans, were you taking some classes with them? Were, was there any--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --none. 

STILL:  Wow.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  None. And that's the thing, none. It, I didn't see them until practice.

STILL:  So when you UK recruited you and Sue came in, you know, what was her whole, what was the whole um recruiting tool then? Did she just want you to, why did they want you at UK? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  They never said, I just took the scholarship and went there hoping for the best. 

STILL:  Wow. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Yeah. And I, I'm seriously hoping for the best. I   wasn't any, just put it like this, the only familiar face was my, the track teacher and her name was Barbara Jean Call. She was, she was (??)--

STILL:  --oh yeah she was the coach, coach the basketball team in the early ‘70s, Barbara did. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  And, and she worked with me as far as track. Her and Sandy Perkins and then Sandy Perkins went on to go to EKU, and that's where, I ended up going there, because I knew she was there, you know. everything had to be familiar with me. And I think that's one of the reasons why I did go to UK because of uh, Miss Call. And like I said, she was in my life at a, at a early stage because they all knew me from running track. And then--

STILL:  So did you run track for UK as well? Well, you know, I tried, but I hadn't found my niche. You know, track in college, you have to really have an event that you're strong in. And I was not as strong in the eight-hundred yard meters   because I, I didn’t, I had stopped training. That was, I had been injured, so I just didn't have that um, a desire. I'm going to say desire to even want to start back. I didn't have a desire to start back running. And I was afraid. You know, when you get hurt in that magnitude, um you have to understand the pain behind it. Uh, we didn't have all that they had, that they have now. We didn't have, I'm going to say we did have um, uh, athletic trainers. But they didn't know as much as they, they knew now. 

STILL:  Uh huh. What about, did you--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --so--

STILL:  --have any interaction with the men's basketball team? Because at that time you guys were so new. I, I guess they're like by the time we get to UK, there is a little interaction with the men's team. There's, when you were at UK, there's, I guess, Jack Givens--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??)--

STILL:  James Lee, um they were all fresh, they were sophomores,   freshmen. They were young as well. Did you see any of those guys, Dwane, Casey, um--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --Jack Givens. And so, you know, I already knew Jack Givens and uh James Lee. And when I would get on when I would get on the court, because I think once or twice we maybe a couple of times we'd maybe play before the men, and I thought they were bullying me. But they were saying, [goose, goose,] because I (??) --(both laugh)-- and I would (??) jumper--(laughs)-- and I would always keep it up there for a while --(laughs)--. But yeah, and I didn't know that, you know. But we didn't have any, any reaction, like, hey, what's up, you know, and talking an, you know, all like that. So we didn't get to, I didn't get to have that experience that I wished I could have had [at UK]--

STILL:  --well, let's, let's get into your actual playing experience. Um, it sounds like, you know, it's already culture shock and just the shock of being, going from high school to college that you're dealing with   as far as your student athlete life. What, what was the routine like with that? Um, I know, were you all practicing at Memorial Coliseum? What were the practices like? What was that kind of structure? And you all start, started probably end of September or so? So--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --right--

STILL:  --from August when you get to uh campus, you don't have any interaction with the team until, what, September, October?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I think we, well, you know what? As I’m thinking, Sue’s office was at the Seaton Center. You remember the Seaton Center? 

STILL:  Uh huh. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  There, her office was at the Seaton Center. Because that's where I met them, in the Seaton Center. And that's where we practiced a lot, in the Seaton Center. We very seldom practice in Memorial Coliseum because that's where the guys practiced--

STILL:  --uh huh--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --and played. And, but we practice at the Seaton Center. 

STILL:  Wow.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  That's where we practiced. Yeah--

STILL:  --When, when did you say that you all eventually moved on the campus, or were you always housed at the hotel downtown that you? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:    Phoenix was the hotel, Phoenix hotel, the Phoenix. And it, we didn't stay in the Phoenix too long. And I, I think that if we were to stay, my mom would make me come back home. But the Phoenix Hotel at the time was where we stayed and we stayed there just a few weeks, maybe a month, and then we moved on into campus. 

STILL:  Wow. So, and where were you living at on campus, where did they, was it Blazer Hall or?  

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --uh yeah, it was one of the halls. It was over there. Matter of fact, it was um, one of the places it was across, really across the street from Memorial Coliseum--

STILL:  --yeah, that's Blazer Hall. Yeah--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --yeah, that's where I was (??)

STILL:  --so then all, and they moved all the players to Blazer Hall at a certain point.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I didn't realize that, because then I moved into another um, dorm. It was right across the street from Blazer Hall and it's set in the middle--

STILL:  --uh huh.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  And then across was the boys basketball team. So I had to come out to the   yard or the court and look over and some of the basketball players would be there. They would be outside--

STILL:  --uh huh--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  So, you know, that's how close it was between where they lived and where I lived. Or a, uh huh, where my dorm was. 

STILL:  Tell us a little bit about practices, the routine. Was there a training table where you got, what was all that like? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Yeah, we had all that at Seaton Hall. I could remember they had uh, we shared with other, the, the other athletes in other um sports, well sport, sport teams, uh you know, and at the time, volleyball was big, volleyball and uh, um, I don't even think they had soccer, but I know they had volleyball and lacrosse. Or was it lacrosse, with a stick?--

STILL:  --field hockey--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --and I remember, they had a--

STILL:  -- field, field hockey probably--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --yeah, field hockey. 

STILL:  Uh huh. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  They had field hockey. And   that's who we shared with, field hockey and volleyball team is what, you know, would always come into contact with and the cross country, of course, and, you know, and some, and track a little bit, but it was most, mostly the uh field hockey and the volleyball. 

STILL:  And you, you all were practicing, what, a couple of hours a day, afternoon, one to three,--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --uh huh--

STILL:  what was your practices like? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  It was, I think was later on. It was later on and after, after everybody they knew that everybody had their last class. And we practiced, we did a lot of running. Um yeah, we had some, we had some pretty good practices. 

STILL:  Uh, were you, because sometimes when you're that young, you don't even recognize this, but were you uh cognizant of you being the only person of color on the team then? Or did that--

WHITE WASHINGTON:  --(??)--

STILL:  --were you aware of, you know, the whole, you know, I, whoa, I'm the only one like me here. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  You know what, and we talked about this   earlier, some mean, a person of my family, uh we wouldn't like to think that. And when I get there, I knew I was different, but color never really came into my mind. It was comp, competing, you know, achieving. Being able, I wanted to play. So I knew that I had to out-play the other girls. But color never came into my mind. It wasn’t a thing that I was thinking about. And people don’t understand that because my mother never really discussed what color I was. It was always, this is what you have. This is how you have to be in order to do this or make it to this point in your life. And we never did discuss color. My mom never just said, well, you got to do this because you that color. Or you got to work hard because you this color, she never said that. It was I was always about self, because you know, preserve, it's just we had to really get it. 

STILL:  So you come in probably with two incredible players, Ceal Barry’s there. She's a   junior and uh, Pam Browning, who can be considered one of the greatest U.K. women's basketball players of all time um, and one of the greatest athletes that, female athletes at UK. What was it like competing against them in practices? Was it a big adjustment from high school or was it just for you? Like you're saying, the color didn't matter. You, you were just out competing. Did, did their ability um, bother you any or influence how you uh went about practices or game? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  No, because I already knew Pam Browning from track because she had she was a she was a high jumper, so I knew Pam, and but when I did compete with these girls, I didn't look at them as being better than I. I was me as being better than they were--

STILL:  --(laughs)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --and, you know, as, as far as um Pam Browning, oh you not going to out-rebound, but you may be almost six-three   or six-four. But you not going to out-jump me. That was just my motto. And I didn't let, I didn't. Intimidation wasn't part of me, it was me intimidating someone else. And that's how I always thought. And that's how, that was my thinking, you know, so I didn't let me. And I was always trying to figure out why, how come I'm not playing? You know? And I didn't, I didn't grasp that content of what, why I wasn't. I'm a freshman and they've been here a lot longer than me. 

STILL:  Mhmm.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  They earned their right to play. But then I didn't understand that part. You know, it should be who's better, you know. But playing basketball comes along with learning plays. Um, and that was one of the things that I realized that I had to do. But then uh, sometimes plays don't always go accordingly, because it could be somebody better than you. Then when they get on you, you're going to have to rethink. You know what I'm supposed to do? This play’s supposed to go like this. I never thought about that.   I would just say, okay, you going to stop me here, that I'm going to go this way, I'm going to do that. And I realize that sometimes maybe they, we weren't on the same wavelength of what, how, what we should have been doing as far as me being a (??) guard, because sometimes I don't want to be a guard. Ceal Barry was going to be the guard--

STILL:  Mhmm.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Sally Bussell, and we had other players that were guards. But I felt like at the post, that was Pam Browning. But how could I help her out? Or how could I, you know, what could I do as a role player? Because I knew at the time that that's what I didn't know what a role player was. But I, a man I can say I was one of the best role players there ever could have been because I knew that I had to come off the bench and when I came off the bench, I was going make a statement. That you're not, if you going to shoot that ball, I'm going to eat it--

STILL:  --(laughs)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --but you're not going to put it in my face. If you're coming down the court and you're dribbling, you're not going to be dribbling out in front of me and thinking I'm not going to steal it.   That's the model that I had. You know, give it to, if you put it out there in front of me, I'm going to take it. And there's times I didn't feel confident about me making the layup, but I’d always give somebody else, because sometimes I would, when I would get the ball, I would be so high up there. I did not realize, now what am I supposed to do with this ball and I'm up here? Lay it in the basket, but it did not always --(laughs)-- happen that way. So I think that my body went first before I could think, you know, have you ever been in that moment, where you like, oh wow, I can do this. But then you realize that after you after it comes in front of you, you're realizing, okay, what am I supposed to do now? You know, you there, you've already stole the ball. You halfway down court. Oh, look at the ball and what I’m supposed to do with it? Because it was always someone else is supposed to shoot the ball. I didn't get that in my head. You know, that I can do this. 

STILL:  And it sounds like, because Sue said you were one of the best athletes on the team, left handed, you were a defensive specialist   at five-four. You're talking about playing in the post. That's ridiculous --(laughs)--. Five-four. It's like, whoa. But I think, and, and she brought in eight freshmens that year. I don't know if you knew that there were eight of you that came in. That the program was so new. So she was probably looking for that competitive nature, you know, who was going to just be willing to do whatever, and it sounds like that was your mentality. You were just going to get out and do whatever was needed for the team. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  And I never thought about sitting on the bench, I didn't want to, but I felt like, well they had been here longer than myself. So then it was okay. But in practice, you're going to earn your spot because I'm going to show you some things, you know, you’re going to earn your spot. You going to be playing before me? You're going to really be in shape when I get through with you because I will really wear you out. And that's the motto that I have to take. No, uh Pam Brown, you're going to go up for a shot? You’re going to eat it today. That's the motto that I had to take running over there, you know, to the uh Seaton Center   when I’m over there and I'm thinking of that, you know what? Uh I mean, I get to start, but guess what you're going to wish I had. And that's just the kind of motto I had. 

STILL:  Did practice--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --you know--

STILL:  --did they, did they get pretty heated? I know with the best teams that I've played with, practices were way harder than, than games. The, the--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Yes--

STILL:  --were there some, you know?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  We, yeah, we, we, we got into some pretty heated, you know. But you know what? I think they were more heated with me than anything because I think I was, thinking about and then, I was a show off. I love to steal the ball, but sometimes after I’d steal it, I didn't know what do with it you know, and I go, I got the ball --(laughs)--, what am I supposed to do with it, you know? And I just love, you know, them going up for a shot and thinking that they had an open shot. And here I come up bam and knock it out of the air. I loved doing that. Uh, and at those times, I really felt like that I should have started, but I --

STILL:  --that freshman year?--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??) why, mhmm I can understand why. It was a lot of freshmen. You know what?   Everybody, and this is what I'm realizing, that we all had our specialties. You know what I mean, I wasn't a, a good shooter. I, it was some that were good shooters. Uh, there's some that couldn't play defense, but they could shoot the world out of the ball, so if I felt like if I, with the defense that I had, and the jumping ability. And if I had a shot that would never miss, I'd be probably starting and never sit, sitting down unless I got hurt or I got tired and I realized that now. And after later on, I had to start playing intramural, I realized my, my strong assets. And my strong assets what I had a beautiful shot. It's just that I had to um specialize and maybe uh flick, flick, flicking my wrist--

STILL:  --what, what--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:   --or getting my (??)--

STILL:  -- type of training where they, where they doing any specialized training to help with your shot? Or, or was it more like you were   the role player coming in? Because there are, there are certain players you're not necessarily concerned about them scoring points. You have Pam Brown and Ceal Barry. So your type of player is come in, you know, stop the other person's, uh you know, star player and then, you know, get the, the garbage player gets the rebounds and, and that's key for a team. Was that your role on the team? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Yes, it was. It was my role to be able to be a top defender, deflecting the ball, getting the ball and then throwing it to the guard and then go positioning myself. And that was what it was all the time. You know, you had your Ceal Barrys that, you know, was to set up the offense. I would have been a more player that not only set up the offense, I could penetrate. And see, that was one of the things that we hadn't been taught, that when you penetrate the middle, you can either dish it off to each side,   left or right, whatever. I put it up. And we did not have that type of coaching of uh, uh, we didn't have the type of coaching. It was not that we was trained to do that. You, you know now, but we didn't have that.

STILL:  Right.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  It was more a set play. You know, and that's the thing. Setting up plays don't always go, and you coach, and you know that if you have a plays, and you set your team to um, maybe throw the ball and cut through, and a lot of times if you got good defensive players, I would never have let. If they cut through, I'm going to say you're going to pay., if you think you're going, if they’re going to throw it to, you know, so that's just, you know, the motto I had to take in (??)--

STILL:  -- hey (??), hey you know, back then, they didn't have million dollar coaches back then. Um Sue Feamster was, you know, running the department, the intramural. She was coaching six, I think, three or four different teams, no experience.   So it's a different, it's a different era. It's you know--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --it was--

STILL:  --you guys were laying the groundwork and most of it was out of a passion for the game and to be recognized, you know, to have the opportunity for women to play. And I think that's, that was what was driving you all, your passion for the game and then that women should have the right to play. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Right. Um, and you know, f you, if you have another thing, too, I think that when you are gifted, what other gifts as far as uh being an athlete? And now you have to decide. Then, you didn't. You didn't have to decide, but you have to decide and, and I think that I'm glad that I didn't have to decide, because if I failed in one thing, I can make it up in another, which was track, because track is more of an individual sport. And I could prove myself   which basketball is a team sport. And even though you want to prove yourself, you, you still have five other players just playing on the floor with you for the players. So that's a big difference--

STILL:  --what--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  -- it’s different with fifteen. Other people are sitting on the bench with you. 

STILL:  What type of conditioning and strengthening were you all doing? Weights? What, what was that like? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I’m trying to (??)--

STILL:  --(??)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??) [drill]. 

STILL:  --(??) drills?--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --no.--

STILL:  --(??)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON: --no.

STILL:  --wow--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  we, we did [drills]. Anything that you did, you did on your own. Uh after, after we would get through, I would run the Coliseum of Memorial Coliseum, I would run. If we was in Seaton Hall, they had a weight room, I would be in there lifting with my legs. And so I would always have to come run over from Blazer to Seaton Hall, so I got my work in uh that way. 

STILL:  Now while--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --but--

STILL:  --while you’re, you all are now practicing on campus and academics   as well, how’s class work going along with you and your student life now that the season started and you all are training and practicing. What was that like for you? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Well--

STILL:  --(laughs)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --it was foreign. It was foreign. I remember my English class. I'm like, I can't do this. And I remember history, I mean, I just remember all my classes, I remember [my] lecture classes and I think once or twice and maybe I may have went to lab. So classes for me was definitely different from classes that you would have in high school because you knew when you had to go, and, and college at UK, I had to find my classes. I didn't even know where half the classes were when I found them the classes were over. So, you know. --(laughs)--

STILL: Wow.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Yeah. Yeah. Mhmm.

STILL:  But--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --and then after that--

STILL:  --[the team] wasn't provided any kind of help in that way or other teammates?--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --no.--

STILL:  --you guys weren't   share with each other. Your experiences, were they keeping an eye? I know when we were there, they had the CATS system where they were (??), that you had to go to class, there was study hall. None of that was happening?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  No.

STILL:   You’re on your own. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  You know, when I, when I got uh, when I was put on academic probation, I didn't know, I got a letter. That was the most embarrassing thing. I cried. Because I'm like, I can't do this. And it wasn't that, I don't think that I couldn't. I just needed help. 

STILL:  Mhmm.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I really needed help. I needed someone to show me how to study, to show me how to write that paper that we have to write in English classes. A lot of things that I just did not know how to do on my own. 

STILL:  Were you keeping it to yourself? Or were you letting anyone know and, or was it? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I kept it to myself. 

STILL:  Did your, did your family know? Were they aware that you were struggling academically and? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Well I didn't want to tell nobody. I didn't want to. I mean,   my family expected great things. And how can you tell your mom, Mom, I don't think I can get this. I didn’t want nobody to know. You know, I wanted to be like the other girls. 

STILL:  Mhmm.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I wanted to have you know, that uh whole um, you know, you want to have all of it. Want to be able to, to play ball, to have the academics. You want to have the whole package. And I think that really being that young, I always concentrated on athletics, I did not really concentrate on my schoolwork because I didn't feel like I had to. I mean I’d not go to class and pass when I was in um high school. It was a different you know, you got different teachers. You know, nothing is required of you. You just knew. You know, everything was on your level. And when you move on to college, it's all academic. It, it’s structured. It's, it's a   lot different, you know so--

STILL:  --and it sounds like with your competitive nature, you know, once you figured out that the academic part was challenging, not because you probably were not able or had the ability, but mainly because you didn't have the wherewithal, you didn't know the system. And so it sounds like you probably it was even worse for you being as competitive, not being able to find a way. To make that work, but you didn't know the system.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Valerie I would cry. I actually cried because I'm like, I can, I want to do it, but I don't know how, I don't know who to talk to. And I couldn't talk to the other players because they were happy and they had their own lives and they were doing their own thing and you know, everybody was into their own self. And I tried to be that. You know, my aunt worked of course, she worked at the student center. And I wanted to go over and talk to her. Sometimes I just want to hang out with the other people,   or look at the other students. So--

STILL:  --and you were telling me, too, that you, speaking about your aunt, that you all had ties to um Dr. Otis Singletary and um, and I guess some of the other people at UK and you all were already familiar, I guess working with them, is that right? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  They were.

STILL:  Your, you’re real--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:   -- my, my, my grandma, my aunt, which I always thought that, you know, she should have been my mom, uh, she worked with the, she loved the football boys, she worked it over there with the football players. And, and she (??) them, and not only that, somebody asked her, what did you what do you think about Adolf Rupp? And she said, well, Adolf Rupp, he's never talked to me of negative, and we talked, and I liked him, so and so and so. So to that, it was how you treated other people. You know? We were, we were. And I'm glad that I was   blessed with that, really not knowing, uh the color barrier. There was color barriers, sure. But my, my, my, family was just Kentucky die hard. Because they work for all of them, my aunts worked for UK or they did something in that aspect. So uh, they just always loved UK. And they thought a lot of me going there and like, oh, you're going to be the first black coach. But they didn't know that, there's things that I really couldn't do. I just didn't want to tell nobody, you know, I'm having a hard time, you know. And I know I disappointed a lot of people because I should, I should have really told someone that I was having problems. But who do you tell or? You know, to me, that was failure. It was failure for me. That I could not produce in that, in that way as far as academics. 

STILL:  Well, let's, let's get into the season, because, I, you know, there's some incredible things going on   in that ‘75, ‘76 season, you all go thirteen and twelve. So it's almost a fifty percent, you know, record there. Uh you play fifteen games away, only ten games at home. Uh tell us a little bit about the season, some of your most memorable games and some of your most memorable uh players that you played against um during that season. Do you remember any in particular? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Yes, I do. I'll never forget her name. Lucy Harris--

STILL: --oh, lord--

WHITE-WASHINGTON: --from Delta State, oh my God. She had to be seven foot. I was like, if I just block her shot I’ll be alright --(laughs)-- and show the world that, I, hey, these little people can get up. And, she was just intimidating. She was just like when you looked at her, you looked at Lewis Alcindor. That's what I looked. Yes, she was, that big, that good. Dunking. She was that good. I'm serious. 

STILL:  Oh, yeah. Delta State. So you travel. You all travel.   That's what you're--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --Mississippi--

STILL:  --you go to I guess that's your Christmas tournament, right?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Mhmm.

STILL:  So you play Golf Coast uh--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --mhmm--

STILL:  --and then you play Delta State and then you play Anderson College. Was that your first trip south? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Yes--

STILL:  --deep south--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --yes. 

STILL:  Tell us about that experience.--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --I remember--

STILL:  --like travel arrangements because, you know--

WHITE WASHINGTON:  --you know--

STILL:  --teams are crazy, like when you're traveling, it's a whole new ballgame. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  You know what, I’m not going to have to say this. Sue Feamster was a very protective coach. And the only thing that I remember is that Sue would always, she always had our backs, she always had my back. To that, I didn't see anything. The only thing that I saw that was a negative that scared me was when that door flung open. I thought that, oh wow, these doors come open on they own. But it wasn't. It was a African-American man   that when we came in the door, he opened the door and they’d be just like, boom, they opened. And then when I would walk through I would kind of look back to it, and there he was and he kind of he looked at me and I looked at him. I’m like, I, I had a funny feeling about I was, I felt funny. I'm like, why are they opening doors? Why are they back there like that? And these are so many things, that's, I was beginning to see things at that time. (??)--

STILL:  --what are you referring to your trip, trip down south? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Yeah, the south. 

STILL:  Yeah.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Yeah. (??) there's things there that you did, that you see that was like, whoa. (??)--

STILL:  Did you all take, of course, it was a bus ride, right? So y-you all traveled with like a--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --we traveled, I think vans, the blue vans that they had. We traveled in vans.

STILL:  Uh huh. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  We all, y’all  used to probably use the bus, I don't remember us using a bus we may have, but I remember them blue vans. So--

STILL:  So two or three vans going down. People going uh --(both laugh)--. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Uh huh. Uh huh.

STILL:    What, what was that like? --

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --it was [fun]--

STILL:  What, what was those bus--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??)--

STILL:  --ride? I know they had to be crazy. I've, I’ve been with teams. You know, there's crazy things going on. What was some of the fun stuff going on in those bus rides of these teenage girls, your first time, um you know, traveling that way? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Well, we sung, laughed, joked. You know we had, it was like this bunch rode together then that bunch. It was always like it was uh whoever was um, everybody had their own circle. So then it was whoever hung with whoever was in that bus, well these are me, and so. And there was times I wanted to ride on the other bus and they would (??) and they’d say, come on, we going to ride on this bus and I really didn't want to ride and I’m like, I don’t want to ride on that bus with her, I’m going to  ride over there with Pam, you know? --(both laugh)-- But I didn't want to hurt her feelings, and so I thought I'd jump on the bus with her. I'm like, ugh, you know what I'm saying? I want, I wanted to get to know everybody. Just, I just didn’t want to be your friend. I wanted to be everybody's friend.   And so, and I was crazy about Pam, you know, but they were on a different level than I was and they were, had their, they had their uh nucleus, people of who they hung with. And then I was with the old freshman kids. So, you know. 

STILL:  Yeah, you were a rookie. What you trying to hang out with the big kid players? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  ‘Cause I felt like I was in that category--

STILL:  --(laughs)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --that I should have been hanging with the big dogs. They were the big dogs. I wanted to be a big dog, too,--

STILL:  --(laughs)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --I feel like, well I can out-play y’all, how come I can't be with the big dogs? And that’s how I felt. You know, I really felt that way. I did.

STILL:  --so you all started off the season pretty strong. You, you lost the first game, but then you win four, I think, three or four. And by the time you go down to this uh, to this Christmas tournament south--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --mhmm--

STILL:  --you end up at Delta State, which Delta State has a, is an historic college for women's basketball. What are some of the most powerful teams um, were coming out of Delta State at that time, including Lusia Harris,  --

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --right.--

STILL:  --who is, you know, legend. So what was that game like? I, I, I noticed you guys, I, I hate to bring this up, but you kind of got blown out there um.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  They got blown out, and they could have used me. They should have let me guard her, wouldn't have had those forty, fifty points --(both laugh)-- you know I laugh about that (??). No wonder. Y'all don't have nobody that can handle her--

STILL:  --well that’s Lusia Harris, what, what are you going to do against Lusia Harris? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Well, you know what I noticed about Lusia Harris? She liked to keep that ball in her midsection and I’d have torn from her every time. Went on down the court, come on Ceal and Sally. 

STILL:  --(laughs)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  You know, that’s, let me coach. Let me do it. And, and I mean, I'd be sitting on a bench just looking, thinking them, take the ball, you know. 

STILL:  Mhmm.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:   She's putting it there for you. Anytime somebody gives you a gift, take it, you know? And so, and I remember that, I remember us going to south and playing and me playing a lot because they didn't expect a little five-four guard to just come up, blam. I would just take the ball.   I would wait for them to come down and throw it. I noticed they always had a person they would throw it to. And I think that, the one time we pulled it out, we really pulled it out. We won. Sue put me in, and I can remember, we pulled it out. I just got the ball, gave it to the girls, and they did their thing. 

STILL:  Was it really popular? I know at Delta State, I'm pretty sure they had big crowd, a big crowd there, but were you all drawing uh attention at UK? It's, it’s a very new varsity sport. And which places that you traveled to? Can you remember um, them having a lot of fans and, and just a lot of support?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I'm thinking. I know we traveled to. You know, we traveled to EKU, or they came to us,--

STILL:  --uh uh--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --it was always a lot of people when, when we played EKU because there was rivalry between   EKU and UK, because uh EKU was, was they were good. They were all, they were, they always beat us. Um, they always had big girls, we had big girls, but they weren't as good as the girls that uh EKU had. Um--

STILL:  How about Tennessee? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Oh I don’t even want to talk about Tennessee. Tennessee--

STILL:  --wasn't Trish was Trish Roberts, you play against Trish Roberts?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I don't remember. 

STILL:  I think she was at Tennessee. She eventually went to the Olympics in ‘76. We'll talk about that as well. But uh, Pat Head, I don't know if Pat Head was at Tennessee at that time. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I think she was, yeah, she was there. Yeah, 

STILL:  --uh, coach. She was coach--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --Pat Head was there--

STILL:  --mhmm--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --because we went down there for tryouts and I can remember her distinctly she's just a very strong coach. 

STILL:  But that overall season, you're, you’re that ’75,   ‘76 season. What do you remember most about it? What, what did you take away from that? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Honestly. It was difficult and it was difficult because it was, it was foreign to me. It was. It was. I, it was hard for me to remember. How it was in basketball because I was suffering from just trying to adapt and being there, and it took away from me playing basketball, it really did. Uh I was, I just was alone, I was lonesome, and I just couldn’t understand why I, I feel so lonesome like this. And then there was times I would have to cry, I would cry like, you know what? I, I think I've made the wrong decision. And when I start seeing these other teams, I realized that. When we started playing other teams, I realized I had made the wrong decision.   That’s, you know, I was, I wasn't really happy, but I like, I like Sue, and when the aca, when I, when I start really, really hurting academically, I knew this is not the place for me. And I think that when I raised my hand and that uh professor told me to meet him after class, come down. And when I did and he did when he talked to me that way, I had never in my life been talked to like that. 

STILL:  What, what did he say to you? 

WHITE-WASHTINGTON:  He told me to, when I went down there. He says, never raise your hand in my class. This is not a class that you raise your hand in, this is a lecture class. If you want to know anything about what I'm, what I have discussed, we have discussed in this class, you come to lab, and that's when I’m wanting to know, lab?  I didn't see no nothing about no lab. And so when I went back and looked at my schedule, it said that lab. I didn't know what a lab was. And see, that's the thing.   You don't know these academic terms that they use. That these terminologies that they use. I didn't know I was, was, I was not familiar with none of that. So that's that. 

STILL:  So you said, was it? Did you go on academic probation during the season or was it after the season? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  It was after that year. I got that letter and then that's when I went to summer school. 

STILL:  Okay. Okay. So you played the whole season and then um went to summer school. So, so they weren't keeping, I know when we were in school, they knew every grade point average--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --mhmm--

STILL:  --and every little iota of what we were doing and study halls and all that. But they, that wasn't in place then with you all. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  It wasn’t in place. And I don't know when it got in place, but it wasn't in place when we went, when I was there, it was not in place at all. And when I got that letter, I was like, oh, I can't tell nobody.   The only person that knew that I wasn't coming back was Debbie Mack.

STILL:  Oh, wow.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Because she went with me to EKU when I went on that visit. 

STILL:  So tell us about that, you, you going on a visit to U, EKU or, and this is why you're still at UK--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --uh huh.--

STILL:  --technically still enrolled at UK.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Uh huh.

STILL:  So tell us how, how that happened. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I just went down there and I talked to uh Sandy, uh Sandy Perkins, uh of course, I didn't talk to any of the coaches, but I went down there and out to look to see if I would really like it. And as soon as I stepped on the campus, I'm like, well, this is all smiles is compared to Kentucky. And then it's just a certain way that you felt, that I felt when I was there. And then after I really talked to Sandy Perkins, I had made up my mind I'm going to sit out, work with, down at the pencil factory, which is in our neighborhood, I’m a work at the pencil factory with my mom, save up my money, and then I'm going, I'm going back that spring semester, which I did. I went back that spring semester.   So I sat out the fall. But what I can truly say is, same as I remember. Sue did call. She wanted to talk to my mom, but I wouldn't talk to anybody. 

STILL:  Wow. So she couldn’t convince you. Sue, wanted you back again? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  She wanted to know how come I wasn’t enrolled--

STILL:  --oh.--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --and I told her that I'm on academic probation. But the best thing and the good thing about me transferring is it allows all those bad courses. Only the good transferred, and then I started over and did well. 

STILL:  Nareen, knowing what you know now, um what would you tell your eighteen year, because you were eighteen, you're a teenager, what would you tell your teenage self um, during that period?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I would have told myself, Nareen, go in there and take Miss Alice Clay’s English class. Get yourself prepared academically, because you about ready to go to the biggest university and things are going to change in your life,   so you have to get yourself academically ready. And then not only that, academically ready, just ready for everything. You know, of course, we don't know these things then, but I just wish that my parents hadn’t sheltered me the way they had. I just wish they had not. (??)--

STILL:  --what would you tell your teenage self at UK, though? That's in high school. You would say prepare yourself better for college--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --teenage self (??)--

STILL:  --okay, what would you say while you get ready to make this decision, keeping things a secret, what would you tell yourself today in that regard? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  This is what I wished I had told myself. I wish that I went to Sue Feamster and said, Sue I'm having a hard time. Do you think I can get some help? Because I'm on probation here. You know, I’m not going to get to be here any longer, I need help. You know, I want to, I want a future here. Can you find me the help that I need to a, achieve my academic, you know? And, and I didn't do that--

STILL:  --because that sounds like  --

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??)--

STILL:  --Sue Feamster had, she had confidence in you, she knew your talent. In fact, in 1976, um for the Olympic tryouts, so this is historic because it's the first Olympics um that women's basketball is going to be in, included in, and so they have these tryouts in April of 1976, they’re regional tryouts over, I read over probably a thousand, because whoever wanted to go out could go out to those. And then they invited a certain amount for um, for like the final tryouts. They only invited thirty four players, plus the twelve players that were already on the USA national team, the Pan Am teams. And Sue Feamster must have put your name in the bunch because you were invited to those tryouts. Tell us a little about that. The, the Olympic tryouts, were you aware of the significance of that? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  You know what, at the time, I was not. I just know that we were going to these tryouts   and I know that uh I wish that I would have known what I've known now and I would have probably made a better showing. Uh--

STILL:  --what did Sue tell you (??)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??)--

STILL:  --about that though, because she arranged that, didn’t she?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  No she [didn’t want to] talk about that. You know she just says, you know, she sent us. And, you know, it wasn't like maybe we should have been more prepared and what was going to go, go on. But it was just like we got there just like big old scrimmage, you know. But, you know, we had to do different things. I think we had to go and um, register and let them, you know, we had to do that. And then they gave us numbers and it was just like two, three. They call your number, you go out there and you do your thing. I just felt like that I didn't get enough time to showcase. I think everybody at the time was showcasing their own selves. (??)--

STILL:  --how, how many players from UK went to that tryout? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  It was Debbie Mack, Ceal Barry, Pam   Browning, and I think Sally Bussell went, so was Sally, yeah, and I think the, the Galloway girls went, yeah. 

STILL:  And you.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Uh huh, myself. 

STILL:  So Sue must have thought that you had a chance at that. I find that just amazing. And it, it sounds like from your, you know, your personality characteristics as a player, she knew you would be able to compete even with names like Pat Head Summitt or Nancy Lieberman, who was still in high school or an Ann Meyers. Um, these are like, Lusia Harris was at that. Tell us about the tryouts. What was that like? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Well, getting your step, getting your chest stepped on on the way up for a layup was some stuff, I was like, what the heck just happened here? I mean, I was just, you know, because I was always good in setting up the offensive play, when they have the ball to charge me, because I was that quick, I could get back and she just   went up and it was like she stepped on my chest and she went up and I'm like, what [in the] world?--

STILL:  --who's who stepped? Who stepped on your chest? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I don't remember who it was--

STILL:  --(laughs)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Who, I didn't even care who it was. My, my, my pride was gone and my whole pride was gone. I'm like, who could, how could I have let somebody do me like this? That is not unheard, that is unheard of. And so then I knew then, I'm up against the stuff. Those girls were awesome--

STILL: --where were those tryouts? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --and there was nothing (??). It was held at the University of Tennessee. 

STILL:  Okay. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Yeah, I remember that. And I remember I sat on a piece of tape. And when I got up, when they call, and when they called my number, when I got up, I was running down a court with his tail hanging, and everybody’s laughing, and I’m like, what they laughing at? And I had a, and somebody came up and just kind of yanked it off. So, you know, I just kind of looked at me, and they just really playing with me. They just I'm just a clown. I'm the clown, you know, just so many things that I think about now. But it was a beautiful experience just seeing the other girls playing and   um, how, how good they were, I was amazed that, hey, I'm good, but y’all are even better. But I could have been as just as, I could have been just as good. It's just that a lot of times you have to find your, your game. You got to find yourself as far as a basketball player, what your strongest assets are and work with that, you know. 

STILL:  --now what about legendary--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??)--

STILL:  --hall of Fame coach Billie Moore? She was the head uh coach. And I think it's, the system was Sue Gunther, who was another Hall of Fame women's basketball coach. Um, do you remember them at all being at those tryouts or interacting with them at all? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  You know what? I really don't remember because it was so many of us.

STILL:  Mhmm.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I don't really remember. I just remember the experience, but now I don't remember and it’s, they let you down that I don't really,   but I don't remember them, you know. I really don't.

STILL:  But, I mean, the, the whole fact that you can say you were invited to the first tryouts for that Olympic, Olympic women's basketball team, national team is just amazing. It’s a, it’s--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --well Valerie, I didn't really know names until later on after you have been there. You’re like, well, I remember her, I remember that, you know, but really, you don't remember things until after you've been there. And then you’re realizing, well, you know what? You was a part of that. May not have went as planned, but you was a part of that, and that's what I felt. I was a part of that. 

STILL:  Did Sue go to those, those tryouts as well, or did she just send players?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  She sent players, she didn't go with us, she sent the players and--

STILL:  --did you all stay together? Um like room together, did you each--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --yes--

STILL:  --go down individually? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  We went, no, we went together. Yeah, she, she made sure of that.   Sue made sure that we all went together, we all, you know, I think somebody was in charge of the money. We all had what we needed. And she didn't send us down there with nothing, she sent us down there we were ready. I can actually say that; she had us together. 

STILL:  Before we go on to your post UK experience, share just a little bit about Pam Browning um on a personal level and on an athlete level. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  On a personal level, I really, I was, oh Pam was she was my girl, she was my dog, you know. You know, we, we, we shared a lot. We talked a lot. Uh Pam Browning was, was very sensitive. Uh I remember when she, when she hurt her foot, you know we all cried, but Pam Browning was one, she was a very athletic person too. Uh and that's where I'm like I said, that's where I met her, in track,   but uh yeah, she was an athletic person, too. So uh to that. And then as far as her be playing with her, oh my goodness. Uh, she was. When I look at her game, and I have to bring you in there, too, but when I look at her game and your game, you know, she was uh. She was a really inside, she was the old fashioned inside post player that, you know, that you can get the ball to her, she was going to finish. She wasn't anything flashy at all. She just could finish well around the rim. Because she was tall and she kept that nice touch. But uh she was my friend off the court and she was my friend um on the court and off the court. And as time went on, I would see her after life, after basketball. You know, after a while I had got to you know, talk with her. And, you know, we worked together at different camps and we got to share. You know,   we had moments that we weren't working, that we got to share different things, talk about different things, talk about our lives. So to that, uh she's a person to be missed. 

STILL:  Awesome. I know this is a question that probably uh it's hard to answer because most of the time, eighteen, nineteen year olders really don't understand the significance, but did you, were you aware of Title IX and--

WHITE-WASHINGTON: --yes--

STILL:  Oh, okay, tell us a little bit about your experience with Title IX, Title IX.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  [Before] at the time of Title IX. Uh, it was uniform, you know, all the guys always had uniforms. So in high school, we finally got our track uniforms and we finally got our basketball uniforms. And I wanted to really compete with the boys, I wanted to play basketball with the boys, and I said, no, ma'am, you all have your own team. You have your own tournaments, you can't play with us.   So that was I, I had to get used to that. But Title IX at the time, yes, we, we, we did get to get things that we didn't get to have, or we didn't have at the time. So that was a big thing. Title IX. Oh it was, Title IX was the biggest step in everything in every phase of life. It was always Title IX, just not in sports but in life, period. You know, everybody wanted to make all the women, wanted to make you know the same amount of money. All the women wanted to the same uniforms that the guys had. We wanted two or three uniforms also. And, and Title IX brought us a little bit. I mean, we did get uniforms. We did get things, some of the things that the guys got to have, but not everything. So.

STILL:  Did it, did the Title IX help any with the stereotypes, the negative connotations of women that participated in sports or that whole, um you know, the way people look? I know I was known as a tomboy my whole you   know, life because I liked sports. How do you navigate that, and was that the same experience as yourself? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Well how I navigated it is that I, I didn't think about uh unfair treatment and I didn't have to because I did my treatment on the court on whatever, whatever, I touched I made sure that I was going to be the best. And no, we didn't have Title IX. Just have to hear what you had to do, which is, your parents at the time had to sign forms, whether or not you could play with the boys, or what. So I think that at that time when Title IX came into play, uh it was, it was good and it was bad. It was good for girls who maybe weren't as in tune and playing uh on, on in a top level as the guys played. And I think that, that we had to prove ourselves       caught up in so many things, you know, I. I ended up on the cross-country team. And basketball, I felt like I had made a mistake in basketball, I got there and basketball was nothing like UK. I'm going to say that. Uh, basketball was nothing like UK. I stayed there for two years and--

STILL:  --in which way, in which way was it not like UK?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  It [wasn’t] really basketball. I wanted, I should have stayed at UK. I realized and everybody told me, you should stay at UK. But what I wanted to say was, well, if you knew that I was not, academic achieving, then you would know I had to go, but I just wished I would have stayed at UK because EKU yes they had a really good team, but at the time UK was coming up. The, UK was coming up because EKU was going down, and when I got to EKU, I just felt like that I'm going to go to what is true to me, and that's track. Because I would watch the girls run   inside because we would be practicing basketball and they'll be up there running them up, watching them, realizing maybe that's where I should be. I'm not feeling comfortable down here with these girls. It's time for me to move on because I really got tired of being the only minority. I did not start realizing, wow, it's hard being a person of color being asked about yourself. That was not an easy task. So I just thought, let's be true to myself, let's just run track and practice on that art and just say forget it, basketball, and that's what I did. 

STILL:  So, were you there for three years at EKU then? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I was there for, yes, I was there. And I, I did all my, I did like those, I was there for summer school for two years on and off. You know, when you get through with your, your spring, then you go into summer, and that's what I did that. So I stayed down there for two years, just never coming home, staying   and uh taking up courses that I didn't do well in. And so uh my sen--my year that I was supposed to graduated I realized I was academically I'm doing fine, but my courses aren't where they should be. I didn't have enough hours that I needed to graduate with girls or graduate with the class that I should have. So I just decided I am so mentally tired. So I just went into the service when I found that I wouldn’t get to graduate. 

STILL:  Wow, how that, you just decided military is the route to go then? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Well, I went and talked to the recruiter first and he tells me said, well, you know, you'd be going in as an officer. --(laughs)-- So I wanted to know what those officers do and he was telling me, I'm like, I don't want to be an officer yet. That’s just like going to college. I needed, I need to rest. I need to rest myself. And that's what I was telling him. He said, then you can go in as a private first class. I said, I'll take the private first class,   which I went in as a private first class. 

STILL:  The [what], you say between an officer and a private first class, you decided the private first class.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  PFC, PFC White. 

STILL:  Uh huh.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  That's what I, that’s who I was. And when I got there, I, I didn't I was like, wow, this is beauty. And it was a rude, it was an awakening for me because that was, I needed structure, I need a rule, I need a structure in my life. And not only that, I needed to know where I'm going. I needed to grow up. I needed to be, to get stronger within who and what I wanted to be. And I felt like that me going into the service that would do it, which when I went into basic training, it was doing it. So basic training to me was just like walking through something. It was just so easy because I was such in shape. You know, I was, I was in shape basic training, was just a walk in the park. So--

STILL:  Because you were so conditioned to um, so self-motivated anyway,   you needed more structure even at UK,--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --mhmm--

STILL:  --it sounds like if you had the structure in place, the system in place, then you would have thrived. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Mhmm.

STILL:  And so the military, it sounds like, provided that for you. Where were you um stationed at? In the military? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I stationed, I was stationed in Fort Ord, California. 

STILL:  Wow.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  And I really, I was supposed to be in a um I was in transportation, and so they said, you know, you're going to draft for the officer and I said, I don't want to draft for the officer. And I'm thinking to myself, I should be an officer and I don't want to draft for an officer, but I really wanted to play basketball. So I went over to the gym and I started playing and they said, who was that girl over there? --(both laugh)-- That's where I met my husband.

STILL:  Uh-oh.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  And so, --(both laugh)-- he was, and so when we, when we, when they would give us orders, he was, they would cut him orders because they needed a center. He was almost seven foot. 

STILL:  Wow. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Yeah. And we would play against each other and   he'd be like, wow, we'd just be playing, you know, giving each other elbows and everything. So we traveled and play ball together. 

STILL:  Was he from Kentucky as well or?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  No, he was from New Jersey.

STILL:  Oh, wow.

WHITE-WASHINGTON: He went to [Mammoth] College--

STILL:  --uh huh, I know exactly where that is, yeah. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  That's where he went. His name is Melvin Hall. 

STILL:  Wow. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Mhmm.

STILL:  So how long did you serve in the military? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Uh, and we just talked about that today. A total of, I got out in ‘86, was a total of six years. 

STILL:  What was that like?--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --and--

STILL:  --did, did you enjoy your military service? Did you, and, and what was--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --when--

STILL:  --the difference between playing in the military because you were playing basketball as well compared to when you were at college? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  You know what, there was a lot of competition in the service. Those girls were tough. Uh, of course, they're in shape, so they're tough and a lot of the places that we played were like Presidio, we played for like on Navy   bases, places like that. Uh, it was, it was awesome, really. The, I think the travel I enjoyed to travel and at the time I enjoyed my husband. So --(laughs)-- but I enjoyed the travel. I enjoyed the travel, uh. 

STILL:  Tell, tell us some of the places that you, you were in active duty. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Uh, active duty, I was just Fort Ord California. I came from out of Fort or California because well what happened, I did not uh pass the physical. I was supposed to take, taking a physical because we were going somewhere and I had to take a physical. And they said, uh, Miss White, you need to come back here. And they said they told me that I was (??), I was with child. And I was like, oh, my God, I'm with child. What am I going to do? --(both laugh)-- How do I get that away? 

STILL:  That’s a [women’s] injury. (??) it’s like--(both laugh)--.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I didn't want to tell anybody. But I knew that's what having problems,   because you getting knocked down on the floor and I’m like oh my goodness, you know, so I decided, you know, I think it's time for me to get out. Well, my uh at the time he wasn't my husband, but we decided that you know, we're going to get married. We going to come back to Kentucky to get married. And I'm going to go in. Um I wanted to go with him to Seoul, Korea, and I didn't go. He went to Seoul, Korea and I stayed home. So that's that and--

STILL:  Wow. It’s amazing to (??)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??)-- I didn't get to get out of service, I had to do my time and uh and I was shocked about how come they didn't let me out of the service? They just gave me orders--

STILL:  --(laughs)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --to--(both laugh)--I thought I was out of the service. They said, oh, no. They gave me orders and I reported at the um over on Leestown Road. But at first it was the Avon. Avon in Lexington, the Army Depot,   Avon.

STILL:  Mhmm.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  That's where we had uh our meet, our uh Army, Army, Army Reserve meeting. So they put me in the reserve. So in the, in the summertime, I would have to go to Fort McCoy, Wisconsin in Fort McCoy. I loved it. I just loved being in the service. And I really felt like that if what didn't happen to me, I probably would have came out an officer. You know, if I would have made the career in the service, if after I got to school. I uh had gotten myself hurt there and I just decided that, you know, it’s time for me to come home. And when I came home, it wasn't, it was different. I, I left myself in, in California. I really left myself in uh Fort Dix, New Jersey. And so when I came home, it was, it wasn't the same as I went in. That’s all I got to say about that. And I'm not you know,   I was talking about that with my counselor today. I'm not ready for that, to talk about that yet. And uh I just know that at this time, the services are doing what they can do to help me get through that time--

STILL:  --fifteen years of service,--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --so.--

STILL:  -- right? You’ve.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  It, you know--

STILL:  --(clears throat)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  -- in anything in life that I really feel that I made a mistake in, I can't take it back, you know. I would, if you asked me if I wish I would have stayed at UK, I wished I been, I would wish I could academically have talked to someone because I would like to have known today what I could have done if I would have stayed there and got my education, if somebody could have helped me. But it could have been bigger than that. I think it's bigger than that, really, it's bigger than that, you know, it's hard enough for African-Americans, but I think that when you go to an unfamiliar place, it's not wanting or used to African-Americans, then   things are different. And at that time, I didn't know that. I couldn't see that. But if I could see it now, yes, it would be different, you know. 

STILL:  But the whole fact that you are the first African-American female to be a scholarship player at UK. Um that in itself and your resiliency, and I know you don't want to go into your details of your you know, military experience or what what's happened there, but it's not always about points and uh games won, and sometimes this is about perseverance and it sounds like, like your, your, your uh journey has been one of perseverance, of kind of navigating and laying, paving the way for Deborah Oden to come in after you. And, you know, so they tweak certain things and maybe they were more with players in general,   you know, kept an eye on players, incorporated certain programs and also students, student athletes had more support. And then Tanya Fogle comes in after that. And the system is a little better because of a Nareen White that had to take the hit the way you did. And then, of course, Valerie Still comes in after that and so on and so on. So, you know, saying that you could have, you know, if things would have been different. You're significant as the first African-American female at UK is still extremely important. How do you feel about that? What, what do you think your legacy in that sense is? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I just hope that my legacy would be that any player of color that has any problem that they have, I hope that they will address it in the right way.   Uh, because it's not easy. Kentucky is not an easy place to play at [as] an African-American. I just hope my legacy will open up doors that if a person is having or if they having complications in anything in their life that they would have a system set up to be able to help that person through that time, because if you looking at all these young girls and boys going through the system, it's not easy. And, and I want that, I hope that now that when we do get there, that they're ready for us when we get there, not just you’re okay, she's been here for a while, but when we get there, embrace us, embrace that person, that person of color who's coming from unknowns. And I hope that they would do that, that the legacy that hey, she opened up the door for other black athletes. You know,   it's and we know that it's not easy. It's not easy going to Kentucky. The stereotyping that has been put there, all the things that have been said. 

STILL:  Do you follow the team today, the program? UK women’s basketball? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  [I do now,] I do now. Um, they have an African-American coach and I want her to succeed and yes, I do. This is the first year really that I have followed them. Because I like her, I think that she deserves a good chance, she deserves a chance and they're good. They're really good, I would like to see them uh be better defensively, more, but other than that, they're a good team, got some good players. 

STILL:  And if you look at the program now and I mean you look at your team, you're the only person of color, only player of color. If you look at the team today, it's a whole different demographic.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --[I] know.

STILL:  Now, on that team and as you said, the head coach, assistant coaches are um   African-American or people of color. Um, you, you see that team now with the protests that were going on this summer, you know, as far as Black Lives Matter--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --right--

STILL:  --they’re taking more of a stand, they're more vocal. Uh do you see your resistance, your protest? It's not protest, but your mode of how can I say this? Uh by breaking that that barrier at UK, how does that compare to what you see going on with the team today and what's happening with women of color um at UK women's basketball? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Well, they have the first African-American coach. 

STILL:  Well, no, Bernadette, remember Bernadette?

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --well Bernadette (??). But I'm talking about being a coach, and maybe I shouldn't say that. I mean, she's out there coaching those girls. That's what I'm saying. 

STILL:  Yeah.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I mean, they may have been first there, but I'm talking about in a job role as I am the lead, I am   the head.

STILL:  Mhmm.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  There's a big difference. Because that's what they going to look at you as. They're going to look at you as, oh, I, I'm helping. They going look at you as, hey, you taking on this responsibility. To be able to achieve um, getting your girls to this point, and that's what, you know, I just think that is uh so amazing that we have now the whole team is African-American, just about. You may not, and they and they're playing bigger roles and into today's sports there. That's the thing. They have big roles now. They didn't have that at, at, when I was there, when we were there. Then they play and they, they are really promoting it more. Having African-Americans in the, and visually, not just to say, oh, um, well, she's here, but then in a bigger role. In a bigger role. Responsibility.     Nareen White-Washington, how, how is things different and how are you impacting youth today? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I am uh, I work with the foster grandmother program here in, in Georgetown and that's important to me because we're working with kids that are in poverty. And my role is to make sure that the kids have been mentored, which most of the kids that are there, they have some type of um IEP, as the school would call it. They have educational needs or they have um some type of needs that they would have when they go to school. They couldn't have academic uh. They may not be able to achieve academically. They may have a stimulation problem, is one of the problems that they may have and what happens there, we have teachers that may not can   be able to work with this child because he has old Johnny over there that needs me in this aspect. So what I do, I come in as a buffer and help this child that is in need that the teacher does not have time to put herself into when you got fifteen other kids. So then I am in charge of going to that child and making sure that that child gets the needs that is necessary. Because he has to be uh, we want to get them to the point to where they are, have social and their social needs, academic needs, and any need that I need to be there to help them with. And you get a lot of kids that are going to abuse, are going through uh being homeless. It’s just so many aspects of him that [dynamic] of what poverty can, how it can affect you, or how it can   affect, you know, the homes of uh single parenting um. And it's hard it's hard being a single parent. And we get most of the kids that come from single parent homes there are maybe having uh financial difficulties or difficulties, period, or abuse. And that that is the most that you probably will see. The kids are being abused and kids are being abused more now than they've ever been. Or, and I’m not, I, maybe I shouldn't say that, but the outcry is louder now. And I want to be a part of that. I want to be a part of not wanting a child to go through what may be something I have gone through in my life. And I can detect that quicker than maybe somebody else can by the experience that I've had in that. So to that, that's my future now, is help, if I can, if I had ten kids and I can get one to come out and be just a brain, that is good. I'm good with that,   but just not one. I'm hoping they all can. All the kids that I work with can come out to be successful. 

STILL:  Wow, and that’s--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --so (??).--

STILL:  --that's right, and that's so powerful, Nareen, because it makes me connect you back to you as an eighteen year old on UK’s campus, uh because we're all, we all have the possibility we have greatness within us. But when a kid doesn't know that or doesn't feel like they have the support or have someone they can talk to, then it changes who they are. And here you are. You've experienced that because like you were saying, if there was a different support system in place, the trajectory of your life might have been much different, not that it would have been better or worse. But now you have that experience. And so there are kids that aren't reaching out. Then they might be internalizing it. And you, with your experience, are able to tap into that. It's, that's a beautiful thing, I think. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:    Well, I think that and this is true. You know, when I took a physical education with a coach, an endorsement. And I feel that, well, you know, you didn't get to that point, but you at a better point because then you can help people that are in need. You can give them the understanding and the love that they may not get outside of, of (??) you know, of what of the center or just school or just whatever. And I see that I see that when young people period, that they need more. And sometimes parents of today, they don't have the time and they don't have the strength sometimes. To sit down and talk to their child. Or their kid could, it could be having a problem that they don't see, that I can see. And so then I tell that kid, you know what, or that child, or the young lady or that young man. You know what?   You're not the only one that has a problem. But what we going to sit here and do is we're going to talk about what we can do to make your problem better. And I want to help you make your problem better. And that's what I feel like I can do. You know, and that's what I want to do, because, like I said, you know, kids are, they always say kids that we can wiser. You know what I hear? I listen to all the time. And I don't know if you (??), you are into gospel music. But my favorite song is “I never could have made it” Warren Sapp. 
I, I listen to that song. All the time, because I knew that. You know, I listen to it all the time, because you know, I need that. I listen to it all the time. So sometimes I just wake up in the morning and play that. So,--

STILL:   Nareen, why, as I told you, I didn't know there existence, existed at Lillian Nareen White. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Mhmm.

STILL:    And why is it that no one knows your story, your history at UK, why, why do you think that is? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Because it's never been told and why, I don't never talk about it. I just got a text, somebody says, I didn't know you went to UK, and this is my family member.--(both laugh)--.I don't talk about it--

STILL:  --(??)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I mean, I don't really talk about it. You know, what is it to talk about? Hey. Hey. So I did (??) and I just, you know, it just so you know, something to boast about, you know, I, I, I didn't get to do what I wanted to do, but this is nothing to me. To me, why boast about it? It’s just something that I've done. And I just don't think about, I don't think about it. I'm only thinking about it, man, because people bring it to the foremost. And when I talk about it, you know, sometimes I don't know what to say. Sometimes I do know what to say. But like my counselor says,   you know, you've done a lot of things in your life. Why don't you talk about ‘em? And I said, because there are stuck points in my life when I say stuck points, stuck points means that a part of your life that was going good and then something happens traumatically that changes the dynamature of everything. And I think that's where, where I told her that's where I am and that's where I was. And now that I'm getting counseling, it's like, oh, wow, the doors are finally opening.

STIL:  Yeah.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I can see. There's times you could, I couldn't see. But now I got to, I'm getting a clearer picture of who I am, what I stand for, what I want to be. And I had to go on a journey. I had to go on a spiritual journey and every other type of journey you ever wanted being in. I had to go on. I had to find out who am I? And why I’m here. And that's   sometimes I cry about it, because I feel like that sometimes life deals you cards, or they tell you a hand, they deal you a hand and you may have a bad hand, but then as you  throwin’ these cards out, you have to figure out what are you going to do with these bad cards? And that's life. I've had to figure out what the hand that has been dealt to me, how am I going to figure this out? How I'm going to do better with this? You know, because sometimes your mind closes and sometimes we don't have a, we have a reset button, but you can push that reset button over and over. And if things don't, if you don't uh, uh adhere to it or if you don't understand when that reset button is pushed, you got to understand which way you are going to go. It’s in front of you, but you have to choose   which fork of the road you're going to take. 

STILL:  Wow. And, you know, you saying that, coming full circle to, you know, what I said earlier about our voice, I think each person has a voice, a story that has to be told. And that's why this UK women's basketball oral history is so important, because sometimes we live with guilt and shame or whatever. You know, you internalize certain things and your voice is squashed and your story is so powerful that no matter how insignificant you think it is, it's not. Because I'm telling you, I appreciate what you did at UK, some people might say, oh, she was only there a year, even if you were just there for an hour or two, being the first African-American woman to get a full scholarship at UK, just paved the way for so many other women. And I'm pretty sure Kyra Elzy uh   is a, a beneficiary of that as well. So um I want to say just thank you. What do you want your legacy to be? When people hear Lillian Nareen White-Washington, what is your legacy? Well, your story. Well, in, in, in a short amount of words. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  For every door that is closed, it's always a door opened. And a lot of times we don't want to go through that door because a lot of times we are afraid what's behind that door, but my legacy is that I can truly say I've made it. I mean, it has not been easy, but that's a barrier that I've crossed. And I feel like that even though that I did try, I, I didn't accomplish it, but I tried it. And that's that what   I want people to feel that it's, always try something that's different, but there's just so much I could really say, and I'm just I'm just really overwhelmed because I have so, I have my mind is really racing and it's a question that I probably have to really think on when you ask, what is my legacy? That's the question I have to really think about. You know, I wished it was different, but I want more than what I have gotten as far as my legacy, um and I just wished I would have I wished that it could have been a time like this that I would have gotten to go to UK. So the legacy that I want to say is that at least I got there. 

STILL:  --you did it.--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  It was what it was, I got there and I got there at a time that African-American women,   I don't think would have came --(laughs)--, but I got there, I'm there, I got there is what I'm going to say. I got there. And I did the dag gone thing. 

STILL:  --(laughs)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I tell you --(laughs)--.

STILL:  You sure did. You sure did.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I say, I tell you, I, I got there. And it was a good run, and I think that I proved myself as a young African-American woman, I proved myself there.

STILL:  --and still proving yourself--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??)-- Huh?

STILL:  And still proving yourself. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I hope so. 

STILL:  --(laughs)--You are--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --Valerie, I [really hope so]. I hope so.

STILL:  Listen, this has been fantastic. Is there anything else that we didn't talk about or, or you were able to share that you, you like to share now? And I don't want to conclude it without you um if there's anything else that you want to share. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  No, not really--

STILL:  --who's your favorite player? No, I'm just kidding. Don’t--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --ah--(both laugh)--

STILL:  Hey  --

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --look, I haven't got there and I see a lot of the players, but I'm like, wait a minute, how is that Rhyne Howard girl? She’s tough. She’s tough.

STILL:  Just come on, come on now. A, a, (??)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --but my favor, I'm a tell you who my flavor, favorite--

STILL:  --let me tell you--


WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --favorite players her name was. Her name was, I think her last name is Still--

STILL:  --thank you, thank you--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --Valerie Still. And I tell you, I would have had a nickname for you--

STILL:  --(laughs)--hey--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --when they say Still I said, hey, let's get this steel together, Valerie’s in the house, let’s get the steel together, you know. So, hey, I would’ve loved to play with you--

STILL:  --you would’ve dinged me up too I bet you would have like okay--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --you know what? Oh, I've been talking to you. Yes, I would have dinged you up. But I will tell you what--

STILL:  --Nareen you would have got the fist elbow from me, fist elbow--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --that’s--

STILL:  --would’ve got it--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --you know what? That would've been a good one because guess what? I even learned how to follow that I, I got better than Dennis Rodman--

STILL:  --(laughs)--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I would, I would have failed back when I saw that. Hey, I'm aware of that, when I saw that elbow about to come out of that, I would've went back. --(laughs)-- and really gotten a hold of my jaw like you really [hit] me.   But I, you know what?--

STILL:  --oh man-- 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --I bet you could’ve, what’s it called when you, dynamic duo, because I--

STILL: --yeah, yeah--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --would’ve ripped that ball off the court, off that rim, and I said, let’s go, girl--

STILL:  --mhmm--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --and we would’ve been running. We would’ve been running--

STILL:  --hey, you got the, got it--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --you got the running game (??)--  

STILL:  --you've got to, hold on. You mentioned Ryan Howard. I, let's end it on her because you're the past of UK’s women's basketball. Ryan Howard, player [of] the year--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --mhmm. Right.

STILL:  Bad woman--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --right.

STILL:  What do you what, what, what's your thoughts on her? 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I think that, you know. She's a very strong, well-rounded player. Um, I, I, I really think that really she needs to work around more around the basket. You know, putting up some shots that, you know, she wouldn't think that she could do, but she's tough around the basket. (??) That's one of the, that’s a strong point if she can get it up, if she can, if she can know how to work around it you know-- 

STILL:  --you know, the game has changed. No one shoots from underneath anymore. It's three point game now. Everybody wants to   shoot the three. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  But you know what? I tell people, some, a lot of times your three point gamer’s not on. So if your three point gamer’s not on, then you going to have to learn other moves that you're--

STILL:  --mhmm--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --going to have to learn how to play around. That's the thing is, teams--

STILL:  --that’s old school--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  I think that teams live and die, live and die by the three point. You're not always on and you have to go inside. 

STILL:  Yeah.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:   I bodily contact with contact, knowing how to put it up without them being able to deflect it. That's the thing. You don't have to, it's like being a magician. 

STILL:  --mhmm--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --and I have to learn, I have to learn Miss Howard how to be a magician with the ball. Then you see it. Then you don't. 

STILL:  I got you.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Great players, great players have learned how to do that. Look at, look at Michael Jordan. Then you see it. And then you don't. 

STILL:  Wow.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  He was a tremendous athlete, and that's the thing about being a basketball player is that it's just not only being a basketball player, she has to be an athlete.   She got to know how to do it all. 

STILL:  Yeah, well, listen, Miss Lillian Nareen White-Washington--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(laughs)--

STILL:  --thank you so very much for sharing your story--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --(??)--

STILL:  Again, this is our new UK women's basketball oral history. And I just appreciate you being here today and taking the time with us. Thank you so much. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Thank you, thank you. Thank you for having me. 

STILL:  Lady Cats for life.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Lady Cats. And we get hey, we're going to have to do a big alumni thing. 

STILL:  Let’s do it.

WHITE-WASHINGTON: (??) I'm serious--

STILL:  --mhmm--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  going to have it. And we're going to call it, we've got to, we got to get a good name for it. And everybody got to come back now--

STILL:  --mhmm--

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  --and we come back and everybody sees us, the gonna like, like, look at them now. How do you like me now? 

STILL:  Oh, yeah.

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  See what I’m saying?

STILL:  Thanks, Nareen. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Thank you. And thank you for you being the person that you are. I got some, I, I've been looking at your book, and I'm like,   you know what, she has to send me that book. 

STILL:  Did you send? Oh, well, okay, we'll talk about that later, I'm going to cut the recording off now. 

WHITE-WASHINGTON:  Oh, okay, I’m sorry --(laughs)--
[[footnotes]]
[[note]] See the Aviary platform here: [link]]https://www.aviaryplatform.com/[[/link]][[/note]]
[[note]] See the Aviary platform here: [link]]https://www.aviaryplatform.com/[[/link]][[/note]]
[[note]] See the Aviary platform here: [link]]https://www.aviaryplatform.com/[[/link]][[/note]]
[[/footnotes]]</transcript>
    <transcript_alt/>
    <rights>RightsStatement</rights>
    <fmt>video</fmt>
    <usage>UsageStatement</usage>
    <userestrict>1</userestrict>
    <xmllocation>MS-Record=ID.xml</xmllocation>
    <xmlfilename>MS-Record=ID.xml</xmlfilename>
    <collection_link>CollectionLink</collection_link>
    <series_link>SeriesLink&#13;
</series_link>
  </record>
</ROOT>
